1️⃣ What is JSP?
JSP (Java Server Pages) is a server-side technology used to create dynamic, platform-independent web pages. It allows embedding Java code directly into HTML pages using special JSP tags.
2️⃣ What is the difference between JSP and Servlet?
Servlet -->	JSP
Java code inside .java file -->	HTML with Java code inside .jsp file
Hard to maintain -->Easier to maintain
Mostly logic -->Mostly presentation
Written manually -->JSP converted internally to Servlet
3️⃣ What is the lifecycle of a JSP page?
Translation phase – JSP is converted into a Servlet.
Compilation phase – The generated Servlet is compiled.
Initialization (jspInit()) – Called once when the JSP is first loaded.
Request processing (_jspService()) – Called for each client request.
Destroy (jspDestroy()) – Called when JSP is unloaded from memory.
4️⃣ What are JSP directives?
Directives give special instructions to the JSP engine.
Page directive: Defines page-dependent attributes
Example: <%@ page language="java" contentType="text/html" %>
Include directive: Includes a file at translation time
Example: <%@ include file="header.jsp" %>
Taglib directive: Declares a custom tag library
Example: <%@ taglib uri="mytags" prefix="t" %>
5️⃣ What are scripting elements in JSP?
Declarations (<%! ... %>) – Define variables/methods.
Scriptlets (<% ... %>) – Add Java code to service method.
Expressions (<%= ... %>) – Output values directly to the client.
6️⃣ What is the difference between <%@ include %> and <jsp:include>?
<%@ include %>	<jsp:include>
Static include (content merged at compile time)	Dynamic include (content included at runtime)
Faster	Slightly slower
Change in included file requires recompilation	Automatically updated
7️⃣ What are implicit objects in JSP?
JSP provides 9 implicit objects that can be used without declaration:
request, response, out, session, application,config,pageContext,page,exception
8️⃣ What is pageContext in JSP?
pageContext provides access to all other implicit objects and acts as a single point of contact for managing attributes in page, request, session, and application scopes.
9️⃣ What are the different scopes available in JSP?
page – Available only in the current page.
request – Available until request is processed.
session – Available during the user session.
application – Available for the entire web app.
🔟 What is the difference between forward and redirect?
Forward	-->Redirect
Done on server-side --> Done on client-side
URL doesn’t change --> URL changes
Faster -->Slower
Uses RequestDispatcher.forward() -->Uses response.sendRedirect()
11️⃣ What is JSTL?
JSTL (JavaServer Pages Standard Tag Library) provides predefined tags for common tasks like iteration, condition checking, formatting, and database access.
<c:forEach var="item" items="${list}">
  ${item}
</c:forEach>
12️⃣ How can we prevent JSP scriptlets and use MVC instead?
Avoid Java code in JSP.
Use Servlets for business logic.
Use JSP only for presentation with EL (Expression Language) and JSTL.
13️⃣ What is Expression Language (EL) in JSP?
EL simplifies access to data stored in scopes.
Example:
${sessionScope.username} or ${user.age}
14️⃣ What is a JSP action tag?
Action tags perform operations at runtime.
<jsp:include> – Includes another resource dynamically.
<jsp:forward> – Forwards request.
<jsp:useBean> – Instantiates or accesses a JavaBean.
15️⃣ What is a JavaBean in JSP?
A reusable Java class with private fields, public getters/setters, and a no-arg constructor.
Used with:
<jsp:useBean id="user" class="com.demo.User" scope="session" />
<jsp:setProperty name="user" property="name" value="Mahesh" />
<jsp:getProperty name="user" property="name" />
16️⃣ How can you handle exceptions in JSP?
Two ways:
Using errorPage and isErrorPage attributes:
<%@ page errorPage="error.jsp" %>
and in error.jsp:
<%@ page isErrorPage="true" %>
<%= exception.getMessage() %>
Using web.xml configuration.
17️⃣ What happens when a JSP page is compiled?
The JSP engine converts the .jsp file into a Java servlet file.
Then it compiles that .java file into a .class file.
That servlet class handles all future requests to that JSP.
18️⃣ What are custom tags in JSP?
Custom tags are user-defined tags written using the Tag interface or TagSupport class.
They help reduce Java code in JSP and promote reusability.
19️⃣ How to disable scripting in JSP?
Set the directive:
<%@ page isScriptingEnabled="false" %>
20️⃣ What is the difference between JSP and HTML?
HTML -->JSP
Static content -->Dynamic content
No server-side processing--> Runs on the server
Cannot connect to databases-->Can connect using JDBC
21️⃣ What are the advantages of JSP over Servlets?
Easier to write and maintain (HTML and Java mixed).
Better separation of concerns (presentation vs logic).
Implicit objects simplify coding.
JSP supports tag libraries and Expression Language (EL).
Can be precompiled for better performance.
22️⃣ What is the role of the jspInit() and jspDestroy() methods?
jspInit() → Called once when the JSP is first initialized. Used for resource setup (like DB connections).
jspDestroy() → Called before JSP is destroyed. Used to release resources.
23️⃣ How can we share data between JSP pages?
You can share data using:
Request scope: request.setAttribute("key", value)
Session scope: session.setAttribute("key", value)
Application scope: application.setAttribute("key", value)
Cookies or hidden form fields
24️⃣ What is the purpose of the <jsp:useBean> tag?
Used to instantiate or access a JavaBean in JSP.
<jsp:useBean id="user" class="com.demo.User" scope="session"/>
If the bean doesn’t exist, it’s created automatically.
25️⃣ How do you set and get JavaBean properties in JSP?
<jsp:setProperty name="user" property="name" value="Mahesh"/>
<jsp:getProperty name="user" property="name"/>
26️⃣ How does JSP handle multithreading?
By default, JSP pages are multi-threaded.
If you want a JSP to handle one request at a time, use:
<%@ page isThreadSafe="false" %>
⚠️ Not recommended because it reduces performance.
27️⃣ What is the difference between ServletContext and ServletConfig?
ServletConfig -->ServletContext
Used for a single servlet/JSP-->Used for the whole web application
Created once per servlet-->Created once per application
Accessed using getServletConfig()-->Accessed using getServletContext()
28️⃣ What is the purpose of the pageContext object?
Provides a single API to access other implicit objects.
Helps manage attributes in page, request, session, and application scopes.
pageContext.setAttribute("name", "Mahesh", PageContext.SESSION_SCOPE);
29️⃣ What is the purpose of the config implicit object?
It is an instance of ServletConfig, providing initialization parameters to the JSP from web.xml.
30️⃣ What is JSP buffering?
JSP uses output buffering to temporarily store the response before sending it to the client.
You can control buffer size using:
<%@ page buffer="16kb" autoFlush="true" %>
31️⃣ What is autoFlush in JSP?
If set to true, buffer automatically flushes when full.
If false, it throws an exception when the buffer overflows.
32️⃣ What is the difference between out and response.getWriter()?
out --> response.getWriter()
JSP-specific --> Generic Servlet writer
Buffered output-->Unbuffered output
Controlled by JSP engine --> Controlled by servlet container
33️⃣ How can we include JavaScript or CSS in a JSP page?
Just like HTML:
<link rel="stylesheet" href="style.css">
<script src="app.js"></script>
Or dynamically using <jsp:include> for common headers.
34️⃣ What is the isErrorPage attribute in JSP?
Used in an error JSP to indicate that it can handle exceptions.
<%@ page isErrorPage="true" %>
<%= exception.getMessage() %>
35️⃣ What is contentType in JSP?
Defines the MIME type of the response.
<%@ page contentType="text/html;charset=UTF-8" %>
36️⃣ What is the difference between JSP Declaration and Scriptlet?
Declaration (<%! %>) --> Scriptlet (<% %>)
Defines variables/methods at class level --> Code runs inside _jspService()
Executed once --> Executed per request
37️⃣ What are custom tag libraries?
Reusable tags created by developers for specific business logic.
They are declared in JSP using:
<%@ taglib uri="customTag.tld" prefix="ct" %>
<ct:customTag/>
38️⃣ How can you include one JSP inside another dynamically?
<jsp:include page="header.jsp" flush="true"/>
39️⃣ What are the different ways to include files in JSP?
Static Include: <%@ include file="header.jsp" %>
Dynamic Include: <jsp:include page="header.jsp" />
40️⃣ What is precompilation of JSP?
Precompiling a JSP means converting it into a servlet before the first request to avoid delay during first-time access.